Welcome  to   the   Economic  Science   Laboratory.
Please  carefully  watch  these  video  instructions
and  follow  along  on  the  paper  copy  at  your
desk.   Welcome  You  are  about  to  participate
in  an   experiment  in  the  economics  of  decision-making.
If  you  listen  carefully,   you  could  earn  a
large  amount  of  money,  that  will  be  paid  to
you  in  cash,  in  private,  at  the  end  of  the
experiment.  It  is  important   that  you  remain
silent,  and  do  not  look  at  other  people's  work.
If  you  have  any  questions,  or  need  any  assistance
of  any  kind,   please  raise  your  hand  and  an
experimenter  will  help  you  out.   During  the
experiment,   do  not  talk,  laugh  or  exclaim  out
loud  and  be  sure  to   keep  your  eyes  on  your
screen  only.  In  addition,   please  turn  off  your
cell  phones,  etc.  and  put  them  away  during
the  experiment.  Anybody  that  violates  these  rules
will  be  asked  to  leave  and  will  not  be  paid.
We  expect,  and  appreciate  your  cooperation.
Agenda   1.  Instructions.   2.  Quiz  (to  make
sure  everyone  understands  the  instructions).  The
quiz  will  consist  of  12  questions.  The  experiment
will  not  begin  until  everyone  has  correctly
answered  all  questions.   3.  Experiment.   4.  Survey.
After  you  have  completed  the  experiment,  you
will  be  asked  to  answer  several  survey  questions
using  the  computer.   5.  Payment.  After  everyone
has  finished  the  survey,  you  will  be  paid  in
cash.   Experiment  Overview  In  the  experiment
today  you  will  be   matched  into  pairs,  and
will  be  asked  to  make  choices.  The  choices
made  by  you  may   affect  both  your  payoff,  as
well  as   the  payoff  of  the  subject  that  you
are  matched  with.  Similarly,  the  choices  of
the  subject  that  you  are  matched  with  may   affect
their  payoff  and  your  payoff.   Experiment  Details
In  the  experiment  today,  you  will  be  working
with  a  fictitious  currency  called  Francs.  You
will  be  paid  in  US  Dollars  at  the  end  of
the  experiment.   Exchange  rate  :  1000  Francs
equals  1  dollar.  This  experiment  consists  of
four  matches,  each  of  which  may  have  a  different
number  of  periods,  and  may  have  different  payoffs.
At  the  beginning  of  each  match,   you  will  be
matched  with  one  other  subject  that  you  have
not  been  matched  with  before.  You  will  remain
anonymous  throughout  the  experiment.  You  will
not  know  the  identity  of  the  subject  that  you
are  matched  with,  and  the  subject  that  you
are  matched  with  will  not  know  your  identity.
The  choices  made  by  you,  and  the  subject  that
you  are  matched  with,  have  no  effect  on  the
payoffs  of  other  pairs  of  subjects,  and  vice
versa.  You  will  remain  matched  with  this   same
subject  until  the  end  of  the  match.  After  you
and  the  subject  that  you  are  matched  with  have
finished  the  match,  please  wait  quietly  for
all  pairs  to  finish  their  match.  Once  all  pairs
have  finished  their  match,  you  will  be   randomly
rematched  with  another  subject  that  you  have
not  been  matched  with  yet,  and  the  next  match
will  begin.   Experimental  Interface  Next,  we
will  go  over  the  experimental  interface.  The
experimental  interface  consists  of  five  components:
1.   The  payoff  table  is  displayed  at  the  top
left  of  the  screen.  The  payoff  table  has  your
choices  (the  rows,   U,  and   D),  and  the  choices
of  the  subject  that  you  are  matched  with  (the
columns,   L,  and   R).  For  any  combination  of
choices  for  you  and  the  subject  that  you  are
matched  with,  there  is  a  payoff.  Your  payoff
is  on  the  left,  and  the  payoff  for  the  subject
that  you  are  matched  with  is  on  the  right.
For  example,  if  you   choose  D,  and  the  subject
that  you  are  matched  with   chooses  L,   then
your  payoff  is  6,  and  the  payoff  for  the  subject
that  you  are  matched  with  is  3.  The  payoff
table  in  the  experiment  today  will  be  different
than  the  one  displayed  here.  In  addition,  the
payoffs  will  remain  the  same  for  all  periods
in  a  single  match,  but  may  change  in  different
matches.  2.   The  summary  of  the  current  period
is  shown  in  the  top  right.  3.   The  summary
of  all  periods  is  shown  below  that.  4.   The
history  of  play  is  displayed  in  the  bottom
half  of  the  screen.  5.   Finally,  the  current
status  is  displayed  across  the  middle  of  the
screen.  The  current  status  tells  you  what  to
do  at  any  point  during  the  experiment.   Specific
Instructions  for  Each  Period  At  any  point  during
a  period,  you  will  see  one  of  three  status
messages:  Status  #1:  Please  select  My  Choice
(U,D)  and  your  guess  for  Other's  Choice  (L,R).
When  you  see  this  status  message,  you  need
to  do  two  things.  1.  Select  a  row  for  your
choice  (in  this  example  either  U,  or  D).   Once
you  have  selected  a  row,  it  will  be  outlined,
and  the  label  'My  Choice'  will  be  added.   My
choice  will  also  be  updated  on  the  period  summary.
2.  Select  the  column  that  you  think  the  subject
that  you  are  matched  with  will  select  (in  this
example  either  L,  or  R).   Once  you  have  selected
a  column,  it  will  be  outlined,  and  the  label
'My  Guess'  will  be  added.   My  guess  will  also
be  updated  on  the  period  summary.  If  you  correctly
guess  the  choice  of  the  subject  that  you  are
matched  with  in  a  given  period,  then  you  will
earn  a  raffle  ticket.  At  the  end  of  each  match,
one  raffle  ticket  will  be  randomly  selected,
and  the  winner  will  receive  a  bonus  of  5  dollars.
Status  #2:  Please  wait  for  the  other  subject
to  finish  making  their  choices.  When  you  see
this  status  message,  please  wait  patiently  for
the  subject  that  you  are  matched  with  to  finish
making  their  choices.  If  the  other  subject  makes
their  choices  before  you  in  a  specific  period,
you  might  not  see  this  status.   Status  #3:
Click  on  the  payoffs  for  this  period  (in  green)
in  the  game  table  to  move  to  next  period.
When  you  see  this  status  message,  all  choices
for  the  period  have  been  made,  and  you  can
view  the  final  results.   The  column  selected
by  the  subject  that  you  are  matched  with  is
highlighted  and  labeled  'Other's  Choice'.  If
your  guess  about  their  choice  was  correct,  then
the  column  will  be  highlighted  in  yellow.   The
entry  of  the  payoff  table  that  is  at  the  intersection
of  the  row  that  you  selected,  and  the  column
that  the  subject  that  you  are  matched  with
selected,  is  highlighted  in  green.  This  entry
displays  the  payoffs  for  the  current  period.
Your  payoff  for  the  period  is  displayed  on
the  left,  and  the  payoff  of  the  subject  that
you  are  matched  with  is  displayed  on  the  right.
At  this  point,  the  period  summary  has  been
updated  to  include   the  choice  of  the  subject
that  you  are  matched  with,   and  the  current
payoffs  for  this  period.  These  choices  have
also  been  added  to  the   history  of  play  at
the  bottom  of  the  screen.  Finally,   the  overall
summary  has  been  updated  to  include   the  total
payoffs  including  this  period,  as  well  as   the
number  of  correct  guesses  you  have  made  about
the  choice  of  the  subject  that  you  are  matched
with.   To  move  on  to  the  next  period,  you
need  to  click  the  payoffs  for  this  period  in
the  game  table,  which  have  been  highlighted
in   green.   Number  of  Periods  Per  Match  The
number  of  periods  in  each  match  will  be  determined
randomly  using  the  following  procedure.  At  the
end  of  each  period,   a  number  will  be  chosen
randomly  from  the  set  of  numbers   {1,2,3,  up
to,  98,  99,  100},  where  each  number  is  equally
likely.   If  the  number  is  1,  then  the  match
will  end.   If  the  number  is  not  1,  then  the
match  will  continue.  The  number  will  always
be  placed  back  into  the  set  after  it  is  drawn.
Thus,  in  any  period  there  is  a  1  percent  CHANCE
that  the  match  will  end,  and  a  99  percent
CHANCE  that  the  match  will  have  another  period.
Therefore,   the  expected  number  of  periods  in
each  match  will  be  100.   This  procedure  has
been  performed  on  the  computer  before  the  experiment.
Therefore,  you  will  not  see  the  number  selected
from  .  To  ensure
that  the  length  of  the  match  is  not  dependent
on  your  play,  the  number  of  periods  for  each
match  has  be  written  on  the  board  before  the
experiment,  and  will  be  uncovered  at  the  end
of  the  experiment.   Payoffs  Your  payoff  at  the
end  of  the  experiment  will  be  the   sum  of
the  payoffs  for  each  period.  In  addition,  you
may  receive  a   bonus  payoff  if  your  raffle
ticket  is  randomly  selected  at  the  end  of  the
match.  These  bonus  payoffs  won't  be   displayed
until  the  end  of  the  experiment.  At  the  end
of  the  experiment,   your  earnings  in  Francs
will  be  converted  into  US  Dollars  and  you  will