Welcome to the Vernon Smith Experimental Economics
Laboratory. Please carefully watch these video instructions
and follow along on the paper copy at your desk. Experiment
Overview. You are about to participate in an experiment
in the economics of decision-making. If you listen
carefully, you could earn a large amount of money,
that will be paid to you in cash, in private, at the
end of the experiment. It is important that you remain
silent, and do not look at other peoples work. If you
have any questions, or need any assistance of any kind,
please raise your hand and an experimenter will help
you out. During the experiment, do not talk, laugh,
or exclaim out loud, and be sure to keep your eyes
on your screen only. In addition, please turn off your
cell phones, et cetera, and put them away during the
experiment. Anybody that violates these rules will
be asked to leave and will not be paid. We expect,
and appreciate your cooperation. Agenda 1. We will
first go over the instructions. 2. Then we will have
a practice match to learn the interface. 3. There will
be a quiz with 10 questions to make sure everyone understands
the instructions. On the quiz, you will be able to
earn up to 50 cents for each of 10 quiz questions,
for a total of 5 dollars. If you answer the question
correctly on your first attempt, you earn 50 cents.
If you answer the question incorrectly on your first
attempt, and correctly on your second attempt, then
you earn 25 cents. If you don’t answer the question
correctly on your first two attempts, you will earn
nothing and the answer will be explained to you. You
must still answer the question correctly to move on
to the next question. 4. After the quiz, the experiment
will begin. In the experiment you will be working with
a fictitious currency called Francs. You will be paid
in US Dollars at the end of the experiment. The exchange
rate today is: 1,500 Francs = 1 US Dollar. Experiment
Details This experiment consists of ten matches. At
the beginning of each match, you will be paired randomly
with one other participant. You will remain matched
with this same participant until the end of the match,
but then will be paired with another randomly selected
participant in the following match. Each match will
have the same structure, but may contain a different
number of periods. You will remain anonymous throughout
the experiment. You will not know the identity of the
participant that you are paired with, and they will
not know your identity. The choices made by you, and
the participant you are paired with, have no effect
on the payoffs of participants in other pairs, and
vice versa. Therefore, your payoff in a given match
is based solely on the choices made by you, and the
participant that you are paired with. Next, Lets Look
at the experimental Interface Specific Instructions
for Each Period Your payoff in each period will depend
on your choice, and the choice of the participant that
you are paired with. You will choose one of two options,
either W or Y. You will be able to see the payoffs
for each combination of choices for you and the participant
that you are paired with. These payoffs will remain
the same throughout the entire experiment (all matches).
The payoffs will be displayed in a table like this:
In this example above, the rows are the following:
Row #1 Your choice. (either W or Y in this example.
) Row #2 Other’s choice. (either W or Y in this example.
) Row #3 Your payoff. Row #4 Other’s payoff. Row
#5 Total number of times that that combination has
been played this match. For example, in the table above,
if you choose W, and the participant you are paired
with chooses Y you receive a payoff of 3, and the other
participant receives a payoff of 4. This combination
has occurred 19 times so far this match. In the table
above, if you choose W, and the participant you are
paired with chooses W, then you receive a payoff of
7, and the other participant receives a payoff of 8.
In the table above, if you choose Y, and the participant
you are paired with chooses Y, then you receive a payoff
of 1, and the other participant receives a payoff of
2. History As the match pro gresses, you will see the
history of play across the top of the screen, displayed
like this: The history tells your choice (labeled My
Choice), the choice of the participant you are paired
with (labeled Other’s Choice), the current period,
and the payoff for the current period. In the above
example, you played W, and the participant you are
paired with played Y in period 39. Rules Rather than
directly making choices of W or Y will develop a set
of rules which will automatically make choices 4 you.
The set of rules will appear in the middle of the screen.
You will be able to construct rules using the rule
constructor at the bottom of the screen. A rule consists
of two parts: Input Sequence sequence of choices by
you and the participant you are paired with. Output
choice to be made by you after the input sequence occurs.
Some example rules are displayed below: For example,
Rule #2 has an input sequence of YY ,WW ,YW, and an
output of W. This means that if you have played Y-W-Y
in the last three periods, and the participant that
you are paired with has played Y-W-W, this rule will
lead you to play W in the next period. The length of
the rule is measured by the length of the input sequence.
Therefore, rule #2 and rule #3 have a length of 3 rule
#4 has a length of 2. There are several ways that you
can modify your rules during the experiment. First,
you can use the rule constructor in the bottom center
of the screen. ] the plus button to add more columns
or one of the minus buttons to subtract columns. on
the question marks to fill in the boxes. When you click
on a question mark, either a W or a Y will appear.
If you click on a W, it will switch to a Y, and if
you click on a Y, it will switch to a W. Once you have
completely filled in the rule (leaving no question
marks), the add rule button will appear, and the rule
can be added to your set. Second, if you look at a
rule in the set, you will notice a green copy button
and a red delete button. If you press the copy button,
it will copy the rule down to the constructor and you
will be able to create a similar rule. If you press
the red delete button it will delete the rule from
the set. Since your rule set needs to make a single
choice each period, it is not possible to have two
different rules with the same input sequence, but with
different outputs. If you create a rule that has the
same input sequence but a different output, you will
get an error that says “Conflicting rule in set,”
and a button that says “Switch Rule” will appear.
If you press this button, it will delete the conflicting
rule from the rule set, and add the rule from the constructor.
A rule of length n is said to fit the history, if the
input sequence matches the last n periods of the history.
For example, since the last three periods of play in
the above history (periods 42 through 44) have been
YY, WW, and YW, and that sequence is also the input
for rule #2, then rule #2 is said to fit the history.
given the above history, we can see that rule #4 fits
the history, ]but rule #3 does not fit the history.
] As play pro gresses you will develop a set of rules
that will be used to make your choices. If more than
one rule fits the history, then the rule with the longer
length will determine the choice. For example, given
the above history, since both rule #2 and rule #4 fit
the history, rule #2 will be used to make your choice
since it is longer. Therefore, given the history, and
the three rules, your choice next period will be W,
as prescribed by rule #2. If no rules fit the history,
then your Default rule will be selected. The default
rule will only be used when no rules fit the history.
To select your default rule, select either W or Y in
the bottom left of your screen. Additionally, you have
to select the First Period rule. The first period rule
will only be used in the first period of the match.
To select your first period rule select either W, or
Y, in the bottom left of your screen. Play will proceed
automatically. Each period, before the choice is made,
the rule that will be used to make the next choice
will be highlighted. The corresponding sequence in
the history will also be highlighted. After the choice
has been made, the statistics for that rule will be
updated, and the corresponding choice in the payoff
table will also be highlighted. Lets look at another
example. In the example above, Rule #4 and Rule #9
both fit the history. However, rule #9 will be selected
because it is longer. Therefore, W will be played in
the next period. For the example above, there are several
ways to make changes to the rule set in order for Y
to be played. First, you can delete Rule #9. Second,
you can add a longer rule that fits the history and
has Y as the output. ] Number of Periods Per Match
The number of periods in each match will be determined
randomly, using the following procedure. At the end
of each period, a number will be chosen randomly from
the set of numbers 1, 2, 3, all the way up to, 18,
19, 20, where each number is equally likely. If the
number is 1, then the match will end. If the number
is not 1, then there will be an additional period.
The number will always be placed back into the set
after it is drawn. Thus, in any period there is a 5%
CHANCE that the match will end, and a 95% CHANCE that
the match will have another period. Therefore, the
expected number of periods in each match will be 20.
You will not see the number selected from the set.
To ensure that the length of the match is not dependent
on your play, the number of periods for each match
has been written on the board before the experiment,
and will be uncovered at the end of the experiment.
Since your choices will be determined automatically
from your rule set, each period will last 10 seconds.
Therefore, the game will progress automatically, even
if you don’t do anything. Additional Information
about Matches During matches 1 through 10, you will
be able to construct the set of rules to make your
choices. All of the rules in your set at the end of
one match will remain in your set at the start of the
next match. Before the first match, you will have 1
c construct your rules. Before every other match,
you will have 2 minutes before play starts to edit
your set of rules. Editing your set of rules In the
experiment today, you will need to pay a cost to edit
rules during the match. More specifically, Before each
match starts: You can change your set of rules for
free before the match starts. During the match: If
you want to make changes to your set of rules during
the match, you can click the “Unlock Rules” button.
The cost of editing your rules during the match is
0 points for clicking the “Unlock Rules” button,
plus 1 point per second that you are editing the rules.
While you are editing your rules, the cost will be
displayed on the “Lock Rules” button, as well as
at the top of the screen. Once you are done editing
your rules, you may click the “Lock Rules” button,
after which point you will no longer incur any costs.
Payoffs At the end of the experiment, you will be paid
in cash. Your payoff at the end of the experiment will
be the sum of the payoffs for each period. Reminder:
the exchange rate today is 1500 Francs equals one US
dollar. Practice Match Next, you will be given the
chance to participate in a practice match, to ensure
that you are comfortable with the interface. It is
important to note that in this practice match, you
will NOT be paid for the choices made in the practice
match. the payoffs are all listed as 0, so that you
can focus on getting comfortable with the interface,
rather than focusing on the payoffs. You are NOT matched
with another participant. Your opponent for the practice
match is a computer that is playing RANDOMLY. Starting
Rules Prior to the start of the experiment, you will
have 10 minutes to construct your starting set of rules.
During that time, you will be presented with a split-screen
view of the construction screen. In this view, you
will have an opportunity to test what your rule set
will select as an output for a variety of hypothetical
histories. The split-screen will consist of two sides.
The right side is the "starting rules" side. Rules
added to this side will be added to your rule set at
the start of the first match. The left side is the
"hypothetical rules" side. Rules added to this side
can be used to test to see what choices different combinations
of rules will lead to. You will be able to move rules
from the Hypothetical Rules side to the Starting Rules
side by clicking the blue move button. To delete rules
from the Starting Rules side you will need to click
delete button. You will be able to see what your hypothetical
and starting rule sets selects as a choice for next
period for hypothetical histories that you construct.
To construct a hypothetical history, you will need
to click on the question marks in that history. Notice
that you will be able to construct and store multiple
histories of different lengths and different choice
sequences at the same time by clicking the New button
or the History number button at the top of the Hypothetical
Rules side. For example, five periods of hypothetical
History number 4 have been filled in. Another example,
14 periods of hypothetical History number 3 have been
filled in. In both examples, you can see what the Hypothetical
Rules and the Starting Rules sets select as a choice
for next period. You will be able to make changes to
your Hypothetical Rules and your Starting Rules for
the duration of the 10 minutes. After the ten minutes
are up, rules that are on the Starting Rules side will
be your starting rules for the experiment. Now that
we have completed the instructions, the Practice match